So now we have as an
intermediate station this state diagram for our
clock and have
seen now in particular
these transitions between such complex
hierarchically or otherwise composite states.
We will first
deal with what
this means in each case
and also which perhaps different possibilities
of such transitions there
are between composite states.
And for this we look first at
what the entry possibilities are into a
hierarchical state of this kind, thus still without
region and first of all only the entry.
Every transition consists potentially of
an exit and an entrance.
Let's have a look at
the very flexible possibilities to
realize the entry
in composite states.
We look at a hierarchical
state, quite times more deeply nested.
There is this
outer nesting level A.
Inside there is a sub-state
C and another sub-state B,
which itself is also composed of D
and E and then other elements appear.
So we will have four
different possibilities to enter here.
The standard entry, that would be the one that
just appeared on the slide for the A transitions.
Then there's explicit entry, where you
don't enter the hierarchical state from the
outside as a whole as
this outer arrow suggests here, but
you explicitly select a sub-state, and
then there are entries via so-called shallow
and deep history, for which somehow
these H or H* nodes are used.
As
a note:
I don't have triggers at
these entry arrows in each
case, in general of course and it
will be the same for the following slides.
In general it would be
possible to specify a trigger here,
like A in
the example here.
There it is an entry and
the arrow says a as a trigger.
You could also imagine
this with these arrows here,
I just didn't
draw it here.
We will come to the
history nodes in a moment.
It is important to note
and also to take into account,
if you create
state diagrams yourself,
that there may be only one outgoing
arrow from each of these H- or H*-nodes.
This is otherwise not the
case for the individual sub-states.
And here are also no triggers
on this arrow only on the entry
arrows or if necessary also
on the arrows here could be
triggers, I have omitted
them in this stylized example.
So let's have a
look at the possibilities now.
We do it
one after the other:
We start with
the standard entry.
The default entry simply ensures that in
each hierarchy level that we have in
the composite state, simply the
respective start state is addressed, or
since there are no parallel regions, simply
the start state of the top hierarchy level.
So in our example, if
we enter this hierarchical state here
via this standard entry,
then that means what?
Then the outermost level start state would
be chosen, which would be this one.
What does
this one do?
It has a transition, a standard
entry, into this composite sub-state B,
because this is also a standard entry via
the start state, the start state present here
would be selected
for this hierarchical level.
That again points to D, i.e.,
the standard entry here would ensure that
ultimately the sub-state D becomes active,
because the start state of the
outer hierarchy level is selected,
that has a standard entry into
this sub-state and there again is
the start state points to D.
So continuation at this entry at
B and in B again at D.
Then there is
the explicit entry.
This simply ensures that the continuation takes place
at exactly the explicitly specified substate, i.e. in
our example it simply leads to
a continuation at C, because this
explicit entry points exactly to C. It could also have pointed to
D or E. In this case, the explicit entry points to C.
It could also have
pointed to D or E.
Then these would have
been the relevant next states.
This possibility of the explicit entry also
means that we don't always need a
start state on every level, if we
always proceed by explicit entry, we wouldn't
have to have start states
everywhere, but we may of course.
There was still this
entrance reality about the
history and these are also
the more complex complicated ones.
We first consider
the deep history.
In which sense is
this historical, so to speak?
There it is about the fact that we
can visit a sub-state and thus also a
composite state several times
by jumping back and forth.
So let's assume, in our example,
that we have already been in one
of these states C,D,E in
one of these innermost sub-states.
Then we have been somewhere else,
perhaps in another component of the
overall state diagram that may have
been drawn in here, and then at
some point we return to hierarchical
state A via this deep history.
What
happens then?
What is supposed to happen then is
in the deep history that exactly the
sub-state of the innermost
level, of a respective
innermost level, is accessed from where we
left the overall state A the last time.
This is what
it says here.
If the composite state, in our case now
the A, was already visited once before, then
the last sub-state of the lowest
possible hierarchy level active there is entered.
If we last left from D, then
we would now also continue again at D.
If we last left from C,
then we would continue at C.
Lowest here means C is already a
non-hierarchical state, so C would also be
its deepest level because there
are no further nested sublevels, while
B, for example, is not a deepest level state
because there are still D and E in there.
The whole thing can also be that we
have to do this per region, so to speak.
Not yet in the example just
now, where we have no regions, but
if we have a hierarchical state with
subregions, then it may also be that we
have to go to the last
active substate in each case per region.
If we have never
been to the hierarchical
state, in this case
A, what happens then?
If we have never been here before
somehow and we come across this entry,
this deep history node, then we wouldn't
know, should we continue at C,D or E,
because we have never been here
anywhere and we haven't remembered anything, then
it is simply followed the
arrow that starts from this H*.
That is the role
of this arrow here.
It doesn't mean that we always go to
E, but only if we come into this
A via this entry here and we've never
been to A before, then this arrow tells us:
Then we
continue at E.
If, on the other hand, we have already
been in C, D or E before we
return here, then we also
continue at the respective place.
This describes the deep history
and similarly, but subtly different,
the shallow history behaves, because there
we also return, if we have already
been in this composite
state, basically back to
where we were before we last left,
however not to the lowest level, but to
the respective of the highest
hierarchy level the last overall state.
So let's imagine in our
example again that the last
time we were here we
were at E, if we
then came over the deepest history
we would continue at E not because
of this arrow but because E
was the last sub-state visited here.
If, on the other hand, we come
across the shallow history, then we look:
We were last in E, but E is
part of B, so in this outermost level, if
we look: what is
the next lower level of
nesting, have we been last in
B because we have been in E.
I.e., if we come over the shallow history,
then we would say, we continue at B.
But to continue at B then means to
take the starting state of B, that is
D, what
is here.
If the composite state A was last
left from E, then we now continue
at B, because B is the top
nesting level, so to speak, in which E
occurs, and to continue at B means to continue at
D, however, because D is the starting state of B.
If one has never been at
all in this composite state, then
one proceeds analogously as
with the deep history, thus
if we have never been at all in
the proximity within A and we come over the
shallow history exactly as with the deep history,
then one simply continues there where this arrow
starts from the H-element and in
the case that would mean to continue
here and that would also mean to
continue at D in the concrete case.
That is the
role of this arrow.
This arrow is not there for us to
always continue at D, so even if this
arrow here were to point to C, for
example, then we would indeed go to C if
we have never been inside A, but if
we have been inside A, for example in E,
then we would actually continue regardless of
where this arrow points, the next time
we enter via the flat
history node at D, because
we would look we have already been
here in E, the outermost overall state in
which E occurs, in which we have already been,
is B and the starting state of B is D.
There one must simply read through these rules very
exactly and follow very exactly and comprehend at the example,
then it becomes clear what the meaning
of the entries is in each case.
Beyond that there are still
further possibilities of the entrance, in
particular there is
the so-called entrance point.
This is shown
in a different way.
We will not
deal with it.
That's a possibility in
the UML state diagrams
that we won't look
at in this lecture.
That was the discussion of
the possibilities that we see here.
That was a hierarchical
state without a region.
Now we still need to look at,
what happens if we have a region state?
Then there are
potentially other possibilities.
I'll leave out the history inputs for now,
so as not to complicate the picture unnecessarily.
However, in the wristwatch example, there
will also be such an entry with
regions where we also
have history in play.
So in a region state there
is still the possibility of standard entry,
still the possibility of explicit
entry, still also cases for shallow
and deep history, which I have not
drawn in here now, and in addition
there is the possibility of entry via
a fork and this is of course the
same kind of fork node
as occurs in activity diagrams.
That's used here
to sort of
target multiple sub-states
in the individual regions.
Here it is obvious that we
are actually jumping to a state in
each region, but this must also
be the case for the other two
possibilities, because for regions we are
always in a substate in both regions.
I.e., although this
default entry looks
like it points to only one region, the
actually points to the entire region state, and
we must also select a substate in
each of the two regions on entry.
The same is true
for the explicit entry.
It explicitly points to a sub-state in
a region, yet when explicitly entering a
region state, we have to
select a state in each region.
So we still have to describe
what that means in each case.
Namely, what are
the rules here?
The default entry
is very simple.
Just like we just took the
starting state of the outermost level
of the hierarchy in the default entry
into a hierarchical state, now we just
take the starting state per region, so if
we come to this region state via this entry
here, then we're just going
to choose the starting state in
each region, so in that case we would be in A
in the first region and in C in the second region.
How about
the explicit entry?
There is also clear, there we obviously want to
be in sub-state B in the first region, but at
the same time we have to
do something in the second region.
What do
we do there?
Obviously we take the start
state of the other region.
So one state of one
region is jumped to directly.
This is done by the explicit entry
and in the regions parallel to it we
take the start state
in each case, so
in our example over this arrow we enter in the
first region in B implicitly in the second region in C.
Then there is the case of the fork and
this is also very obvious, because via the fork we
address a special state in each region,
so if we enter via this fork, then
of course we will choose B as the
substate in the first region, and D as
the substate in the second region, because that
is exactly what this representation here gives us.
These are all cases except for the fact
that we would also still have the possibility
to link
regions and history.